A Finding Aid to the Harriet Blackstone Papers, 1870-1984, in the Archives of American Art AAA.blacharr
Archives of American Art
Harriet Blackstone papers
1870-1984
AAA.blacharr
Archives of American Art
5.4 Linear feet
Blackstone, Harriet, 1864-1939
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reels 1617, 1621-1622 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.
Biographical/Historical note
Harriet Blackstone (1864-1939) was a painter in New York, New York. Blackstone was born on November 13th, 1864 in New Hartford, New York. In 1883, she moved to Illinois where she became a high school elocution teacher. She did not start her studies to be an artist until 1903 when she enrolled at the Pratt Institute of Art in Brooklyn, New York. While there her art teacher was William Merritt Chase. Later, Blackstone went to the Academie Julian in Paris, France to gain more experience with Jean Paul Laurens as her instructor. Blackstone started to gain attention as a renowned artist in 1907 when her painting, Soldat de Crimée, was exhibited in The Salon, Paris. She moved back to Glencoe, Illinois and focused more on her artwork by painting commissions and joining different art organizations, such as the Chicago Society of Artists and the Arts Club. Blackstone travelled to different locations, including Taos, New Mexico and Bruges, Belgium, to help inspire her creativity. In 1920, Blackstone moved back to New York City where she would spend the remainder of her life; she never married or had children. She died on March 16, 1939 and was survived by her brother and friends. During her art career, Blackstone often painted portraits of well-known people and over time she developed her own style of work. Her artwork was displayed in several prominent cities in the United States: Washington, D.C., Chicago, Philadelphia, Pittsburgh, and New York City. Some of Blackstone’s artwork became part of permanent collections, such as Soldat de Crimée, which was acquired by the National Gallery of Art in 1921, now known as the Smithsonian American Art Museum.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter Harriet Blackstone date from 1870-1984 and measure 5.4 linear feet. The collection provides documentation of Harriet Blackstone’s career through scattered biographical material; personal and professional correspondence, including letters from Maria Oakey Dewing, Thomas Wilmer Dewing, Alice Tisdale Hobart, Joseph Cummings Chase, Stell Anderson, Mary Landis, Esther Morgan McCullough, and Booker T. Washington; writings by Blackstone, Esther Morgan McCullough, Richard P. Wunder, and Florence Holbrook; personal business records; clippings, exhbition material, and other printed material; one scrapbook; photographs of Blackstone, family, friends, and notable artists William Merrit Chase, Jean Paul Laurens, and John Singer Sargent; artwork; and three sketchbooks. Also found are a few artifacts found on Blackstone's easel.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 9 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1930-1973 (Box 1, 6; 7 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1883-1984 (Box 1; 0.4 Linear Feet)
Series 3: Writings, 1861-1979 (Boxes 1-2; 1.0 Linear Feet)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, circa 1906-late 1930s (Box 2; 0.2 Linear Feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1901-1984 (Boxes 2-3, 6; 0.8 Linear Feet)
Series 6: Scrapbook, circa early 1900s (Boxes 3, 6; 0.2 Linear Feet)
Series 7: Photographs, 1870-early 1900s (Boxes 3-4, 6, BV 7, 8-9; 1.7 Linear Feet)
Series 8: Artwork, 1870-1929 (Boxes 4-5; 0.2 Linear Feet)
Series 9: Artifacts, circa early 1900s-1939 (Box 5, Artifact; 0.4 Linear Feet)
Related Archival Materials note
Also at the Archives of American Art is the Richard Wunder research material on Harriet Blackstone.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Microfilmed material transferred in 1978 from the National Collection of Fine Arts, who had acquired it in 1967 along with Harriet Blackstone's paintings from Stell Anderson, Blackstone's friend and a collector of her work. Anderson had received the papers from Blackstone's brother, Edward, in 1939. Upon Anderson's death, additional material was turned over to her niece Pat Rauchenstein, who donated them in 1989. Prior to the donation, the papers were in possession of Esther McCullough, who annotated some items and added research material in preparation for her unpublished manuscript "Harriet Blackstone, 1864-1939."
Anderson, Stell; Chase, Joseph Cummings, 1878-1965; Chase, William Merritt, 1849-1916; Dewing, M. O. (Maria Oakey), 1855-1927; Dewing, Thomas Wilmer, 1851-1938; Hobart, Alice Tisdale, 1882-1967; Holbrook, Florence; Landis, Mary; Laurens, Jean-Paul, 1838-1921; McCullough, Esther Morgan; Sargent, John Singer, 1856-1925; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915; Wunder, Richard P.; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Women artists--New York (State)--New York
- Biographical Material, circa 1930-1973; Series 1; 7 Folders Box 1, 6
  Scope and Contents note
  Most of the documents found here include personal information on Blackstone such as biographical writings for Who’s Who and information about Blackstone’s artwork, estate documents, and her passport. Biographical notes are written by Blackstone.
  - Bibliography, circa 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Summaries, circa 1937-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Estate Document, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Exhibitions Harriet Blackstone was Represented, 1906-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Passport, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oversize List of Guests, circa early 1900s (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, circa 1883-1984; Series 2; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Arrangement note
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by surname of the correspondents. Four or more letters signed by the same correspondent are housed in their own folder; three or less letters signed by the same person are housed in the alphabetical folder according to their surname.
  This series contains Blackstone's personal and professional correspondence. Letters from family and friends tend to be about praising Harriet Blackstone’s work, encouraging visits, or experiences of daily life. Notable correspondence is with Maria Oakey Dewing, Thomas Wilmer Dewing, Alice Tisdale Hobart, Joseph Cummings Chase, Stell Anderson, Mary Landis, Esther Morgan McCullough, Booker T. Washington, among others. Professional correspondence is primarily about her artwork: coordinating with curators and museums to buy or show her work, Blackstone receiving confirmation about her artwork in competitions, and legal information.
  - A, circa 1920-1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anderson, Stell, circa 1939-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - B, circa 1883-1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Blackstone, Harriet to others, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - C, circa 1902-1937 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Campbell, John A., circa 1930-1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chase, Joseph Cummings, 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - D, circa 1922-1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dewing, Maria Oakey, 1921-1924 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dudensing, Leroy, circa 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - E, circa 1917-1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - F, circa 1908-1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Furness, Clifton, circa 1928-1932 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - G, circa 1922-1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Gay, William F., 1929 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - H, circa 1919-1938 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Heyman, Katherine Ruth, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Humiston, Grace, circa 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - J, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Jones, C. Lansing, circa 1904-1906 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Jules-Bois, H.A., circa 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - K, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - L, circa 1929-1938 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Landis, Mary, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - M, circa 1930-1937 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - McCullough, Esther Morgan, circa 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Mechlin, Leila, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - N, 1937-1943 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - O, circa 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - P, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Partridge, Charlotte Russell, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - R, circa 1906-1936 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - S, circa 1909-1936 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - T, circa 1917-1930 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Thorne, Louie, circa early 1930s (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - U, circa 1911 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - V, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Vayana, Nunzio, circa 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - W, circa 1931-1984 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Washington, Booker T., 1915 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Y, 1937-1983 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Zetterberg, A.P., 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Unidentified Correspondents, circa 1905-1940 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Writings, 1861-1979; Series 3; 1 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Folders are arranged to represent the personal writings of Harriet Blackstone first and then writings about her. Unless otherwise noted, the writings are written by Harriet Blackstone.
  Writings include Harriet Blackstone’s personal notes, hand written and typed, and two lectures on "Modern Art through the Ages" and "Modern Spanish Painters." This series also contains writings about Blackstone written by other authors. Esther Morgan McCullough wrote a biography about Blackstone and the first four drafts and complete typescript are included. McCullough’s biography notes and chronology notes concerning Blackstone are also available in this series. A few years after Blackstone’s death, Richard P. Wunder created a detailed catalog of Blackstone’s work, a draft of which is also found here. Additionally, there are handwritten publicity extracts and "The Painter’s Bruges" by traveling companion, Florence Holbrook, which describes a class taught by William Merrit Chase in Bruges, Belgium in 1912. The memoir is ilustrated with photographs taken by Blackstone of Chase, John Singer Sargent, and others.
  - Notes, circa 1910-1930s (Box 1, Folder 50-55)
  - "Modern Spanish Painters" lecture and notes, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - "Modern Art through the Ages" lecture and notes, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Writings about Harriet Blackstone, 1909-1942 (Box 1, Folder 58-59)
  - "Harriet Blackstone: American Artist" by Esther Morgan McCullough Typescript, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - "Harriet Blackstone: American Artist" by Esther Morgan McCullough Draft 1, circa 1941 (Box 1, Folder 61-63)
  - "Harriet Blackstone: American Artist" by Esther Morgan McCullough Draft 2, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - "Harriet Blackstone: American Artist" by Esther Morgan McCullough Draft 3, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
  - "Harriet Blackstone: American Artist" by Esther Morgan McCullough Draft 4, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Biography Notes by Esther Morgan McCullough, circa late 1930s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Harriet Blackstone's Chronology by Esther Morgan McCullough, circa late 1930s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Catalogue of Works by Harriet Blackstone" by Richard P. Wunder, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - "The Painter's Bruges" by Florence Holbrook, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Publicity Extracts, circa 1922 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Publicity Extracts, circa 1919-1936 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Publicity Extracts, circa 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1906-late 1930s; Series 4; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Personal business records include financial information about Harriet Blackstone’s artwork and professional activities. Also included are European copyright documents, gallery invitations, lists of Blackstone’s paintings in permanent collections, and Blackstone’s own inventory of her artwork.
  - Alphabetical List of Portraits by Harriet Blackstone, circa late 1930s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Consignment Receipts, circa late 1930s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Gallery Invitations and Memberships, 1907-1911 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Harriet Blackstone's Inventory, circa early 1900s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Harriet Blackstone's Painting's Alphabetically Indexed, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Harriet Blackstone's Personal Record of Paintings, 1906-1921 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Insurance Documents, 1929-1940 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - List of Harriet Blackstone Paintings, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - List of Paintings and Price Lists, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - List of Paintings with Notes by Harriet Blackstone, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Lists of Paintings in Permanent Collections, circa late 1930s (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Permission to Copy in European Galleries, 1906-1912 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Stock Documents, 1925-1947 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Printed Material, 1901-1984; Series 5; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, 6
  Found here are various publication documenting Blackstone's career including exhibition announcements, catalogs, and visiting cards as well as two published books Blackstone compiled. Additionally there are journals, magazines, newspaper clippings, and a museum catalog (most are written in English and a couple in French) that depict the artwork of Blackstone.
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1919-1984 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1910-1941 (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - Visiting Cards, 1909-1934 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Book, New Pieces that Will Take Prizes in Speaking Contests compiled by Harriet Blackstone, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Book, The Best American Orations of Today compiled by Harriet Blackstone, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The International Studio, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Artists Guild, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fine Arts Journal, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The American Magazine of Art, 1918-1922 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The National Arts Club, 1933-1939 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Le Nouvelle Revue, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Le Messager de New York Revue Franco: Americaine, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Columns, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Weekly Magazine of New York Life, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Art Digest, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Art News, 1934-1941 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Oversized items housed in Box 6, Folder 2
  - Reproduction of Harriet Blackstone's Work, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Bennington Museum Catalogue, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1908-1984 (Box 3, Folder 15-20)
  - Miscellaneous, 1922-circa 1930s (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
    Oversized items housed in Box 6, Folder 3
  - Oversized The Art News from Box 3, Folder 12, 1934-1941 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Oversize Miscellaneous from Box 3, Folders 21-22, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Scrapbook, circa early 1900s; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 3, 6
  Found here is a large scrapbook that contains clippings, cards, announcements, notes, and photos of Harriet Blackstone. One folder contains a page of the scrapbook that was separated from the main document.
  - Scrapbook Pages, Undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Oversize Scrapbook, circa early 1900s (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Photographs, 1870-early 1900s; Series 7; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 3-4, 6, BV 7, 8-9
  Photographs of Blackstone, her family, and friends can be found here as well as photos of other artists whom had an influence on her including William Merrit Chase, Jean Paul Laurens, and John Singer Sargent. There are travel photos of Blackstone’s experiences in Belgium, New Mexico, New York, and Illinois as well as photos of the studios Blackstone worked in, a subject she worked with, and photos and negatives of her own artwork: paintings, sketches, and drawings. A photo album with separate descriptions can be found here.
  Glass plate negatives are housed in separate containers and are closed to researchers.
  - Harriet Blackstone, 1877-circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
  - Family, 1870-1883 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Others, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - William Merritt Chase, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - John Singer Sargent, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Places, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
  - New Hartford, New York, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Taos, New Mexico, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Bruges, Belgium, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Studio in Glencoe, Ilinois, 1908-1920 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Studio on 15 West 67th Street, New York City, circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Brooklyn Museum Exhibit, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - National Arts Club Studio, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Studio in Hotel Chelsea, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Subject: A Soldier of the Crimea, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Sketches of G.K. Chesterton, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Self-Portraits, Drawings, and Sketches, circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Artwork, circa early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 44-47)
  - Artwork, circa early 1900s (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    Oversized items housed in Box 6, Folder 5
  - Artwork, Mounted on Glass, 1881 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Artwork, Mounted on Wood, circa early 1900s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Negatives, circa early 1900s (Box 4, Folder 6-9)
  - Harriet Blackstone's Photo Album Descriptions, circa early 1900s (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Oversized items housed in Box 6, Folder 6
  - Oversize Artwork, circa early 1900s (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Oversize Harriet Blackstone's Photo Album Descriptions from Box 4, Folder 10, circa early 1900s (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Oversize Photograph Album, circa early 1900s (Box BV 7)
  - Glass Plate Negatives of Artwork, circa early 1900s (Box 8)
  - Glass Plate Negatives of Artwork, circa early 1900s (Box 9)
- Artwork, 1870-1929; Series 8; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 4-5
  This series contains original artwork by Harriet Blackstone including framed paper dolls she made when she was five years old, loose sketches, and three of her own sketchbooks that contain pencil sketches of people. There is also a silhouette of Blackstone created by another artist and a framed pastel self-portrait.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  - Paper Dolls, circa 1870 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbook, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1909 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Sketchbook, circa early 1900s (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Sketches, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Silhouette of Harriet Blackstone by Webster, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Pastel Self-Portrait of Harriet Blackstone, circa early 1900s (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Artifacts, circa early 1900s-1939; Series 9; 0.4 Linear feet Box 5, Artifact
  Found here are objects Harriet Blackstone used in her studio to create her artwork. Included are two palettes, a brush with fine hair, glasses, a calligraphy ink holding case, and various small art tools. Each item is placed in an envelope and foldered with similar objects. The original envelopes that contained the objects are included and remain close to the artifacts they originally held.
  - Artifacts found on Easel, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Palettes, circa early 1900s (Box Artifact)